<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="security">

  <title><ph audience="standalone">Impala Security</ph><ph audience="integrated">Overview of Impala Security</ph></title>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <data name="Category" value="Security"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Impala"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Concepts"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Auditing"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Governance"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Authentication"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Authorization"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Administrators"/>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>

  <conbody>

    <p>
      Impala includes a fine-grained authorization framework for Hadoop, based on Apache Ranger.
      Ranger authorization was added in Impala 3.3.0. Together with the Kerberos
      authentication framework, Ranger takes Hadoop security to a new level needed for the requirements of
      highly regulated industries such as healthcare, financial services, and government. Impala also includes
      an auditing capability which was added in Impala 1.1.1; Impala generates the audit data which can be
      consumed, filtered, and visualized by cluster-management components focused on governance.
    </p>

    <p>
      The Impala security features have several objectives. At the most basic level, security prevents
      accidents or mistakes that could disrupt application processing, delete or corrupt data, or reveal data to
      unauthorized users. More advanced security features and practices can harden the system against malicious
      users trying to gain unauthorized access or perform other disallowed operations. The auditing feature
      provides a way to confirm that no unauthorized access occurred, and detect whether any such attempts were
      made. This is a critical set of features for production deployments in large organizations that handle
      important or sensitive data. It sets the stage for multi-tenancy, where multiple applications run
      concurrently and are prevented from interfering with each other.
    </p>

    <p>
      The material in this section presumes that you are already familiar with administering secure Linux systems.
      That is, you should know the general security practices for Linux and Hadoop, and their associated commands
      and configuration files. For example, you should know how to create Linux users and groups, manage Linux
      group membership, set Linux and HDFS file permissions and ownership, and designate the default permissions
      and ownership for new files. You should be familiar with the configuration of the nodes in your Hadoop
      cluster, and know how to apply configuration changes or run a set of commands across all the nodes.
    </p>

    <p>
      The security features are divided into these broad categories:
    </p>

    <dl>
      <dlentry>

        <dt>
          authorization
        </dt>

        <dd>
          Which users are allowed to access which resources, and what operations are they allowed to perform?
          Impala relies on the open source Ranger project for authorization. By default (when authorization is not
          enabled), Impala does all read and write operations with the privileges of the <codeph>impala</codeph>
          user, which is suitable for a development/test environment but not for a secure production environment.
          When authorization is enabled, Impala uses the OS user ID of the user who runs
          <cmdname>impala-shell</cmdname> or other client program, and associates various privileges with each
          user. See <xref href="impala_authorization.xml#authorization"/> for details about setting up and managing
          authorization.
        </dd>

      </dlentry>

      <dlentry>

        <dt>
          authentication
        </dt>

        <dd>
          How does Impala verify the identity of the user to confirm that they really are allowed to exercise the
          privileges assigned to that user? Impala relies on the Kerberos subsystem for authentication. See
          <xref href="impala_kerberos.xml#kerberos"/> for details about setting up and managing authentication.
        </dd>

      </dlentry>

      <dlentry>

        <dt>
          auditing
        </dt>

        <dd>
          What operations were attempted, and did they succeed or not? This feature provides a way to look back and
          diagnose whether attempts were made to perform unauthorized operations. You use this information to track
          down suspicious activity, and to see where changes are needed in authorization policies. The audit data
          produced by this feature can be collected and presented in a user-friendly form by cluster-management
          software. See <xref href="impala_auditing.xml#auditing"/> for details about setting up and managing
          auditing.
        </dd>

      </dlentry>
    </dl>

    <p outputclass="toc"/>

    <p audience="integrated">
      These other topics in the <cite>Security Guide</cite> cover how Impala integrates with security frameworks
      such as Kerberos, LDAP, and Ranger:
      <ul>
        <li>
          <xref href="impala_authentication.xml#authentication"/>
        </li>

        <li>
          <xref href="impala_authorization.xml#authorization"/>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
  </conbody>
</concept>
