<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="install">

  <title><ph audience="standalone">Installing Impala</ph><ph audience="integrated">Impala Installation</ph></title>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <data name="Category" value="Impala"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Installing"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Administrators"/>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>

  <conbody>

    <p>
      <indexterm audience="Cloudera">installation</indexterm>
      <indexterm audience="Cloudera">pseudo-distributed cluster</indexterm>
      <indexterm audience="Cloudera">cluster</indexterm>
      <indexterm audience="Cloudera">DataNodes</indexterm>
      <indexterm audience="Cloudera">NameNode</indexterm>
      <indexterm audience="Cloudera">Cloudera Manager</indexterm>
      <indexterm audience="Cloudera">impalad</indexterm>
      <indexterm audience="Cloudera">impala-shell</indexterm>
      <indexterm audience="Cloudera">statestored</indexterm>
      Impala is an open-source add-on to the Cloudera Enterprise Core that returns rapid responses to
      queries.
    </p>

    <note>
      <p>
        Under CDH 5, Impala is included as part of the CDH installation and no separate steps are needed.
        <ph audience="standalone">Therefore, the instruction steps in this section apply to CDH 4 only.</ph>
      </p>
    </note>

    <p outputclass="toc inpage"/>
  </conbody>

  <concept id="install_details">

    <title>What is Included in an Impala Installation</title>

    <conbody>

      <p>
        Impala is made up of a set of components that can be installed on multiple nodes throughout your cluster.
        The key installation step for performance is to install the <cmdname>impalad</cmdname> daemon (which does
        most of the query processing work) on <i>all</i> DataNodes in the cluster.
      </p>

      <p>
        The Impala package installs these binaries:
      </p>

      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>
            <cmdname>impalad</cmdname> - The Impala daemon. Plans and executes queries against HDFS, HBase, <ph rev="2.2.0">and Amazon S3 data</ph>.
            <xref href="impala_processes.xml#processes">Run one impalad process</xref> on each node in the cluster
            that has a DataNode.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <p>
            <cmdname>statestored</cmdname> - Name service that tracks location and status of all
            <codeph>impalad</codeph> instances in the cluster. <xref href="impala_processes.xml#processes">Run one
            instance of this daemon</xref> on a node in your cluster. Most production deployments run this daemon
            on the namenode.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li rev="1.2">
          <p>
            <cmdname>catalogd</cmdname> - Metadata coordination service that broadcasts changes from Impala DDL and
            DML statements to all affected Impala nodes, so that new tables, newly loaded data, and so on are
            immediately visible to queries submitted through any Impala node.
<!-- Consider removing this when 1.2 gets far in the past. -->
            (Prior to Impala 1.2, you had to run the <codeph>REFRESH</codeph> or <codeph>INVALIDATE
            METADATA</codeph> statement on each node to synchronize changed metadata. Now those statements are only
            required if you perform the DDL or DML through an external mechanism such as Hive <ph rev="2.2.0">or by uploading
            data to the Amazon S3 filesystem</ph>.)
            <xref href="impala_processes.xml#processes">Run one instance of this daemon</xref> on a node in your cluster,
            preferably on the same host as the <codeph>statestored</codeph> daemon.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <p>
            <cmdname>impala-shell</cmdname> - <xref href="impala_impala_shell.xml#impala_shell">Command-line
            interface</xref> for issuing queries to the Impala daemon. You install this on one or more hosts
            anywhere on your network, not necessarily DataNodes or even within the same cluster as Impala. It can
            connect remotely to any instance of the Impala daemon.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ul>

      <p>
        Before doing the installation, ensure that you have all necessary prerequisites. See
        <xref href="impala_prereqs.xml#prereqs"/> for details.
      </p>
    </conbody>
  </concept>

</concept>
