<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept rev="1.1" id="invalidate_metadata">

  <title>INVALIDATE METADATA Statement</title>
  <titlealts audience="PDF"><navtitle>INVALIDATE METADATA</navtitle></titlealts>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <data name="Category" value="Impala"/>
      <data name="Category" value="SQL"/>
      <data name="Category" value="DDL"/>
      <data name="Category" value="ETL"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Ingest"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Metastore"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Schemas"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Tables"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Developers"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Data Analysts"/>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>

  <conbody>

    <p>
      <indexterm audience="hidden">INVALIDATE METADATA statement</indexterm>
      Marks the metadata for one or all tables as stale. Required after a table is created through the Hive shell,
      before the table is available for Impala queries. The next time the current Impala node performs a query
      against a table whose metadata is invalidated, Impala reloads the associated metadata before the query
      proceeds. This is a relatively expensive operation compared to the incremental metadata update done by the
      <codeph>REFRESH</codeph> statement, so in the common scenario of adding new data files to an existing table,
      prefer <codeph>REFRESH</codeph> rather than <codeph>INVALIDATE METADATA</codeph>. If you are not familiar
      with the way Impala uses metadata and how it shares the same metastore database as Hive, see
      <xref href="impala_hadoop.xml#intro_metastore"/> for background information.
    </p>

    <p conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/syntax_blurb"/>

<codeblock>INVALIDATE METADATA [[<varname>db_name</varname>.]<varname>table_name</varname>]</codeblock>

    <p>
      By default, the cached metadata for all tables is flushed. If you specify a table name, only the metadata for
      that one table is flushed. Even for a single table, <codeph>INVALIDATE METADATA</codeph> is more expensive
      than <codeph>REFRESH</codeph>, so prefer <codeph>REFRESH</codeph> in the common case where you add new data
      files for an existing table.
    </p>

    <p conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/internals_blurb"/>

    <p>
      To accurately respond to queries, Impala must have current metadata about those databases and tables that
      clients query directly. Therefore, if some other entity modifies information used by Impala in the metastore
      that Impala and Hive share, the information cached by Impala must be updated. However, this does not mean
      that all metadata updates require an Impala update.
    </p>

    <note>
      <p conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/catalog_server_124"/>
      <p rev="1.2">
        In Impala 1.2 and higher, a dedicated daemon (<cmdname>catalogd</cmdname>) broadcasts DDL changes made
        through Impala to all Impala nodes. Formerly, after you created a database or table while connected to one
        Impala node, you needed to issue an <codeph>INVALIDATE METADATA</codeph> statement on another Impala node
        before accessing the new database or table from the other node. Now, newly created or altered objects are
        picked up automatically by all Impala nodes. You must still use the <codeph>INVALIDATE METADATA</codeph>
        technique after creating or altering objects through Hive. See
        <xref href="impala_components.xml#intro_catalogd"/> for more information on the catalog service.
      </p>
      <p>
        The <codeph>INVALIDATE METADATA</codeph> statement is new in Impala 1.1 and higher, and takes over some of
        the use cases of the Impala 1.0 <codeph>REFRESH</codeph> statement. Because <codeph>REFRESH</codeph> now
        requires a table name parameter, to flush the metadata for all tables at once, use the <codeph>INVALIDATE
        METADATA</codeph> statement.
      </p>
      <p conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/invalidate_then_refresh"/>
    </note>

    <p conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/refresh_vs_invalidate"/>

    <p conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/usage_notes_blurb"/>

    <p>
      A metadata update for an <codeph>impalad</codeph> instance <b>is</b> required if:
    </p>

    <ul>
      <li>
        A metadata change occurs.
      </li>

      <li>
        <b>and</b> the change is made from another <codeph>impalad</codeph> instance in your cluster, or through
        Hive.
      </li>

      <li>
        <b>and</b> the change is made to a metastore database to which clients such as the Impala shell or ODBC directly
        connect.
      </li>
    </ul>

    <p>
      A metadata update for an Impala node is <b>not</b> required when you issue queries from the same Impala node
      where you ran <codeph>ALTER TABLE</codeph>, <codeph>INSERT</codeph>, or other table-modifying statement.
    </p>

    <p>
      Database and table metadata is typically modified by:
    </p>

    <ul>
      <li>
        Hive - via <codeph>ALTER</codeph>, <codeph>CREATE</codeph>, <codeph>DROP</codeph> or
        <codeph>INSERT</codeph> operations.
      </li>

      <li>
        Impalad - via <codeph>CREATE TABLE</codeph>, <codeph>ALTER TABLE</codeph>, and <codeph>INSERT</codeph>
        operations.
      </li>
    </ul>

    <p>
      <codeph>INVALIDATE METADATA</codeph> causes the metadata for that table to be marked as stale, and reloaded
      the next time the table is referenced. For a huge table, that process could take a noticeable amount of time;
      thus you might prefer to use <codeph>REFRESH</codeph> where practical, to avoid an unpredictable delay later,
      for example if the next reference to the table is during a benchmark test.
    </p>

    <p conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/example_blurb"/>

    <p>
      The following example shows how you might use the <codeph>INVALIDATE METADATA</codeph> statement after
      creating new tables (such as SequenceFile or HBase tables) through the Hive shell. Before the
      <codeph>INVALIDATE METADATA</codeph> statement was issued, Impala would give a <q>table not found</q> error
      if you tried to refer to those table names. The <codeph>DESCRIBE</codeph> statements cause the latest
      metadata to be immediately loaded for the tables, avoiding a delay the next time those tables are queried.
    </p>

<codeblock>[impalad-host:21000] &gt; invalidate metadata;
[impalad-host:21000] &gt; describe t1;
...
[impalad-host:21000] &gt; describe t2;
... </codeblock>

    <p>
      For more examples of using <codeph>REFRESH</codeph> and <codeph>INVALIDATE METADATA</codeph> with a
      combination of Impala and Hive operations, see <xref href="impala_tutorial.xml#tutorial_impala_hive"/>.
    </p>

    <p>
      If you need to ensure that the metadata is up-to-date when you start an <cmdname>impala-shell</cmdname>
      session, run <cmdname>impala-shell</cmdname> with the <codeph>-r</codeph> or
      <codeph>--refresh_after_connect</codeph> command-line option. Because this operation adds a delay to the next
      query against each table, potentially expensive for large tables with many partitions, try to avoid using
      this option for day-to-day operations in a production environment.
    </p>

    <p conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/permissions_blurb"/>
    <p rev="">
      The user ID that the <cmdname>impalad</cmdname> daemon runs under,
      typically the <codeph>impala</codeph> user, must have execute
      permissions for all the relevant directories holding table data.
      (A table could have data spread across multiple directories,
      or in unexpected paths, if it uses partitioning or
      specifies a <codeph>LOCATION</codeph> attribute for
      individual partitions or the entire table.)
      Issues with permissions might not cause an immediate error for this statement,
      but subsequent statements such as <codeph>SELECT</codeph>
      or <codeph>SHOW TABLE STATS</codeph> could fail.
    </p>

    <p conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/hdfs_blurb"/>

    <p>
      By default, the <codeph>INVALIDATE METADATA</codeph> command checks HDFS permissions of the underlying data
      files and directories, caching this information so that a statement can be cancelled immediately if for
      example the <codeph>impala</codeph> user does not have permission to write to the data directory for the
      table. (This checking does not apply when the <cmdname>catalogd</cmdname> configuration option
      <codeph>--load_catalog_in_background</codeph> is set to <codeph>false</codeph>, which it is by default.)
      Impala reports any lack of write permissions as an <codeph>INFO</codeph> message in the log file, in case
      that represents an oversight. If you change HDFS permissions to make data readable or writeable by the Impala
      user, issue another <codeph>INVALIDATE METADATA</codeph> to make Impala aware of the change.
    </p>

    <p conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/usage_notes_blurb"/>

    <p rev="1.2.4">
      This example illustrates creating a new database and new table in Hive, then doing an <codeph>INVALIDATE
      METADATA</codeph> statement in Impala using the fully qualified table name, after which both the new table
      and the new database are visible to Impala. The ability to specify <codeph>INVALIDATE METADATA
      <varname>table_name</varname></codeph> for a table created in Hive is a new capability in Impala 1.2.4. In
      earlier releases, that statement would have returned an error indicating an unknown table, requiring you to
      do <codeph>INVALIDATE METADATA</codeph> with no table name, a more expensive operation that reloaded metadata
      for all tables and databases.
    </p>

<codeblock rev="1.2.4">$ hive
hive&gt; create database new_db_from_hive;
OK
Time taken: 4.118 seconds
hive&gt; create table new_db_from_hive.new_table_from_hive (x int);
OK
Time taken: 0.618 seconds
hive&gt; quit;
$ impala-shell
[localhost:21000] &gt; show databases like 'new*';
[localhost:21000] &gt; refresh new_db_from_hive.new_table_from_hive;
ERROR: AnalysisException: Database does not exist: new_db_from_hive
[localhost:21000] &gt; invalidate metadata new_db_from_hive.new_table_from_hive;
[localhost:21000] &gt; show databases like 'new*';
+--------------------+
| name               |
+--------------------+
| new_db_from_hive   |
+--------------------+
[localhost:21000] &gt; show tables in new_db_from_hive;
+---------------------+
| name                |
+---------------------+
| new_table_from_hive |
+---------------------+</codeblock>

    <p conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/s3_blurb"/>
    <p conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/s3_metadata"/>

    <p conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/cancel_blurb_no"/>

    <p rev="kudu" conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/kudu_blurb"/>
    <p conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/kudu_metadata_intro"/>
    <p conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/kudu_metadata_details"/>

    <p conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/related_info"/>
    <p>
      <xref href="impala_hadoop.xml#intro_metastore"/>,
      <xref href="impala_refresh.xml#refresh"/>
    </p>

  </conbody>
</concept>
