<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="s3_skip_insert_staging" rev="2.6.0 IMPALA-3452">

  <title>S3_SKIP_INSERT_STAGING Query Option (<keyword keyref="impala26"/> or higher only)</title>
  <titlealts audience="PDF"><navtitle>S3 SKIP INSERT STAGING</navtitle></titlealts>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <data name="Category" value="Impala"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Impala Query Options"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Amazon"/>
      <data name="Category" value="S3"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Performance"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Developers"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Data Analysts"/>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>

  <conbody>

    <p rev="2.6.0 IMPALA-3452">
      <indexterm audience="hidden">IMPALA_S3_SKIP_INSERT_STAGING query option</indexterm>
    </p>

    <p>
      Speeds up <codeph>INSERT</codeph> operations on tables or partitions residing on the
      Amazon S3 filesystem. The tradeoff is the possibility of inconsistent data left behind
      if an error occurs partway through the operation.
    </p>

    <p>
      By default, Impala write operations to S3 tables and partitions involve a two-stage process.
      Impala writes intermediate files to S3, then (because S3 does not provide a <q>rename</q>
      operation) those intermediate files are copied to their final location, making the process
      more expensive as on a filesystem that supports renaming or moving files.
      This query option makes Impala skip the intermediate files, and instead write the
      new data directly to the final destination.
    </p>

    <p conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/usage_notes_blurb"/>

    <note type="important">
      <p>
        If a host that is participating in the <codeph>INSERT</codeph> operation fails partway through
        the query, you might be left with a table or partition that contains some but not all of the
        expected data files. Therefore, this option is most appropriate for a development or test
        environment where you have the ability to reconstruct the table if a problem during
        <codeph>INSERT</codeph> leaves the data in an inconsistent state.
      </p>
    </note>

    <p>
      The timing of file deletion during an <codeph>INSERT OVERWRITE</codeph> operation
      makes it impractical to write new files to S3 and delete the old files in a single operation.
      Therefore, this query option only affects regular <codeph>INSERT</codeph> statements that add
      to the existing data in a table, not <codeph>INSERT OVERWRITE</codeph> statements.
      Use <codeph>TRUNCATE TABLE</codeph> if you need to remove all contents from an S3 table
      before performing a fast <codeph>INSERT</codeph> with this option enabled.
    </p>

    <p>
      Performance improvements with this option enabled can be substantial. The speed increase
      might be more noticeable for non-partitioned tables than for partitioned tables.
    </p>

    <p conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/type_boolean"/>
    <p conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/default_true_1"/>

    <p conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/added_in_260"/>

    <p conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/related_info"/>
    <p>
      <xref href="impala_s3.xml#s3"/>
    </p>

  </conbody>
</concept>
