<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept rev="1.1" id="invalidate_metadata">

  <title>INVALIDATE METADATA Statement</title>

  <titlealts audience="PDF">

    <navtitle>INVALIDATE METADATA</navtitle>

  </titlealts>

  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <data name="Category" value="Impala"/>
      <data name="Category" value="SQL"/>
      <data name="Category" value="DDL"/>
      <data name="Category" value="ETL"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Ingest"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Metastore"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Schemas"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Tables"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Developers"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Data Analysts"/>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>

  <conbody>

    <p>
      The <codeph>INVALIDATE METADATA</codeph> statement marks the metadata for one or all
      tables as stale. The next time the Impala service performs a query against a table whose
      metadata is invalidated, Impala reloads the associated metadata before the query proceeds.
      As this is a very expensive operation compared to the incremental metadata update done by
      the <codeph>REFRESH</codeph> statement, when possible, prefer <codeph>REFRESH</codeph>
      rather than <codeph>INVALIDATE METADATA</codeph>.
    </p>

    <p>
      <codeph>INVALIDATE METADATA</codeph> is required when the following changes are made
      outside of Impala, in Hive and other Hive client, such as SparkSQL:
      <ul>
        <li>
          Metadata of existing tables changes.
        </li>

        <li>
          New tables are added, and Impala will use the tables.
        </li>

        <li>
          The <codeph>SERVER</codeph> or <codeph>DATABASE</codeph> level Ranger privileges are
          changed.
        </li>

        <li>
          Block metadata changes, but the files remain the same (HDFS rebalance).
        </li>

        <li>
          UDF jars change.
        </li>

        <li>
          Some tables are no longer queried, and you want to remove their metadata from the
          catalog and coordinator caches to reduce memory requirements.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>

    <p>
      No <codeph>INVALIDATE METADATA</codeph> is needed when the changes are made by
      <codeph>impalad</codeph>.
    </p>

    <p>
      See <xref href="impala_hadoop.xml#intro_metastore"/> for the information about the way
      Impala uses metadata and how it shares the same metastore database as Hive.
    </p>

    <p>
      Once issued, the <codeph>INVALIDATE METADATA</codeph> statement cannot be cancelled.
    </p>

    <p conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/syntax_blurb"/>

<codeblock>INVALIDATE METADATA [[<varname>db_name</varname>.]<varname>table_name</varname>]</codeblock>

    <p>
      If there is no table specified, the cached metadata for all tables is flushed and synced
      with Hive Metastore (HMS). If tables were dropped from the HMS, they will be removed from
      the catalog, and if new tables were added, they will show up in the catalog.
    </p>

    <p>
      If you specify a table name, only the metadata for that one table is flushed and synced
      with the HMS.
    </p>

    <p conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/usage_notes_blurb"/>

    <p>
      To return accurate query results, Impala need to keep the metadata current for the
      databases and tables queried. Therefore, if some other entity modifies information used by
      Impala in the metastore, the information cached by Impala must be updated via
      <codeph>INVALIDATE METADATA</codeph> or <codeph>REFRESH</codeph>.
    </p>

    <p conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/refresh_vs_invalidate"/>

    <p>
      Use <codeph>REFRESH</codeph> after invalidating a specific table to separate the metadata
      load from the first query that's run against that table.
    </p>

    <p conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/example_blurb"/>

    <p rev="1.2.4">
      This example illustrates creating a new database and new table in Hive, then doing an
      <codeph>INVALIDATE METADATA</codeph> statement in Impala using the fully qualified table
      name, after which both the new table and the new database are visible to Impala.
    </p>

    <p>
      Before the <codeph>INVALIDATE METADATA</codeph> statement was issued, Impala would give a
      <q>not found</q> error if you tried to refer to those database or table names.
    </p>

<codeblock rev="1.2.4">$ hive
hive&gt; CREATE DATABASE new_db_from_hive;
hive&gt; CREATE TABLE new_db_from_hive.new_table_from_hive (x INT);
hive&gt; quit;

$ impala-shell
&gt; REFRESH new_db_from_hive.new_table_from_hive;
ERROR: AnalysisException: Database does not exist: new_db_from_hive

&gt; INVALIDATE METADATA new_db_from_hive.new_table_from_hive;

&gt; SHOW DATABASES LIKE 'new*';
+--------------------+
| new_db_from_hive   |
+--------------------+

&gt; SHOW TABLES IN new_db_from_hive;
+---------------------+
| new_table_from_hive |
+---------------------+</codeblock>

    <p>
      Use the <codeph>REFRESH</codeph> statement for incremental metadata update.
    </p>

<codeblock>
> REFRESH new_table_from_hive;
</codeblock>

    <p>
      For more examples of using <codeph>INVALIDATE METADATA</codeph> with a combination of
      Impala and Hive operations, see
      <xref
        href="impala_tutorial.xml#tutorial_impala_hive"/>.
    </p>

    <p conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/hdfs_blurb"/>

    <p>
      By default, the <codeph>INVALIDATE METADATA</codeph> command checks HDFS permissions of
      the underlying data files and directories, caching this information so that a statement
      can be cancelled immediately if for example the <codeph>impala</codeph> user does not have
      permission to write to the data directory for the table. (This checking does not apply
      when the <cmdname>catalogd</cmdname> configuration option
      <codeph>--load_catalog_in_background</codeph> is set to <codeph>false</codeph>, which it
      is by default.) Impala reports any lack of write permissions as an <codeph>INFO</codeph>
      message in the log file.
    </p>

    <p>
      If you change HDFS permissions to make data readable or writeable by the Impala user,
      issue another <codeph>INVALIDATE METADATA</codeph> to make Impala aware of the change.
    </p>

    <p rev="kudu" conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/kudu_blurb"/>

    <p conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/kudu_metadata_intro"/>

    <p conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/kudu_metadata_details"/>

    <p conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/related_info"/>

    <p>
      <xref href="impala_hadoop.xml#intro_metastore"/>,
      <xref
        href="impala_refresh.xml#refresh"/>
    </p>

  </conbody>

</concept>
