<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="intro_client">

  <title>Impala Client Access</title>

  <titlealts audience="PDF">

    <navtitle>Client Access</navtitle>

  </titlealts>

  <conbody>

    <p>
      Application developers have a number of options to interface with Impala. The core
      development language with Impala is SQL. You can also use Java or other languages to
      interact with Impala through the standard JDBC and ODBC interfaces used by many business
      intelligence tools. For specialized kinds of analysis, you can supplement the Impala
      built-in functions by writing user-defined functions in C++ or Java.
    </p>

    <p>
      You can connect and submit requests to the Impala through:
    </p>

    <ul>
      <li>
        The impala-shell interactive command interpreter
      </li>

      <li>
        The Hue web-based user interface
      </li>

      <li>
        JDBC
      </li>

      <li>
        ODBC
      </li>
    </ul>

    <p>
      Impala clients can connect to the Coordinator Impala Daemon (<codeph>impalad</codeph>) via
      HiveServer2 over HTTP or over the TCP binary. Both HTTP and binary support the Kerberos
      SPNEGO and LDAP for authentication to Impala. See below for the default ports and the
      Impala flags to change the ports.
    </p>

    <p>
      <simpletable frame="all" relcolwidth="1.0* 1.03* 2.38*"
        id="simpletable_tr2_gnt_43b">

        <strow>

          <stentry><b>Protocol</b>

          </stentry>

          <stentry><b>Default Port</b>

          </stentry>

          <stentry><b>Flag to Specify an Alternate Port</b>

          </stentry>

        </strow>

        <strow>

          <stentry>HTTP</stentry>

          <stentry>28000</stentry>

          <stentry><codeph>&#8209;&#8209;hs2_http_port</codeph>

          </stentry>

        </strow>

        <strow>

          <stentry>Binary TCP</stentry>

          <stentry>21050</stentry>

          <stentry><codeph>&#8209;&#8209;hs2_port</codeph>

          </stentry>

        </strow>

      </simpletable>
    </p>

    <p>
      Each <codeph>impalad</codeph> daemon process, running on separate nodes in a cluster,
      listens to <xref href="impala_ports.xml#ports">several ports</xref> for incoming requests:
    </p>

    <ul>
      <li>
        Requests from <codeph>impala-shell</codeph> and Hue are routed to the
        <codeph>impalad</codeph> daemons through the same port.
      </li>

      <li>
        The <codeph>impalad</codeph> daemons listen on separate ports for JDBC and ODBC
        requests.
      </li>
    </ul>

    <section id="section_egg_wjt_f3b">

      <title>Impala Startup Options for Client Connections</title>

      <p>
        Use the following flags when starting Impala Daemon coordinator to control client
        connections to Impala.
      </p>

      <dl>
        <dlentry>

          <dt>
            --accepted_client_cnxn_timeout
          </dt>

          <dd>
            Controls how Impala treats new connection requests if it has run out of the number
            of threads configured by <codeph>--fe_service_threads</codeph>.
            <p>
              If <codeph>--accepted_client_cnxn_timeout > 0</codeph>, new connection requests
              are rejected if Impala can't get a server thread within the specified (in seconds)
              timeout.
            </p>

            <p>
              If <codeph>--accepted_client_cnxn_timeout=0</codeph>, i.e. no timeout, clients
              wait indefinitely to open the new session until more threads are available.
            </p>

            <p>
              The default timeout is 5 minutes.
            </p>

            <p>
              The timeout applies only to client facing thrift servers, i.e., HS2 and Beeswax
              servers.
            </p>
          </dd>

        </dlentry>

        <dlentry>

          <dt>
            --disconnected_session_timeout
          </dt>

          <dd>
            When a HiveServer2 session has had no open connections for longer than this value,
            the session will be closed, and any associated queries will be unregistered.
            <p>
              Specify the value in hours.
            </p>

            <p>
              The default value is 1 hour.
            </p>

            <p>
              This flag does not apply to Beeswax clients. When a Beeswax client connection is
              closed, Impala closes the session associated with that connection.
            </p>
          </dd>

        </dlentry>

        <dlentry>

          <dt>
            --fe_service_threads
          </dt>

          <dd>
            Specifies the maximum number of concurrent client connections allowed. The default
            value is 64 with which 64 queries can run simultaneously.
            <p>
              If you have more clients trying to connect to Impala than the value of this
              setting, the later arriving clients have to wait for the duration specified by
              <codeph>--accepted_client_cnxn_timeout</codeph>. You can increase this value to
              allow more client connections. However, a large value means more threads to be
              maintained even if most of the connections are idle, and it could negatively
              impact query latency. Client applications should use the connection pool to avoid
              need for large number of sessions.
            </p>
          </dd>

        </dlentry>

        <dlentry>

          <dt>
            --hs2_http_port
          </dt>

          <dd>
            Specifies the port for clients to connect to Impala server over HTTP.
            <p>
              The default port is 28000.
            </p>

            <p>
              You can disable the HTTP end point for clients by setting the flag to
              <codeph>0</codeph>.
            </p>

            <p>
              To enable TLS/SSL for HiveServer2 HTTP endpoint use
              <codeph>--ssl_server_certificate</codeph> and <codeph>--ssl_private_key</codeph>.
              See <xref
                href="impala_ssl.xml#ssl"/> for detail.
            </p>
          </dd>

        </dlentry>

        <dlentry>

          <dt>
            --idle_client_poll_period_s
          </dt>

          <dd>
            The value of this setting specifies how frequently Impala polls to check if a client
            connection is idle and closes it if the connection is idle. A client connection is
            idle if all sessions associated with the client connection are idle.
            <p>
              By default, <codeph>--idle_client_poll_period_s</codeph> is set to 30 seconds.
            </p>

            <p>
              If <codeph>--idle_client_poll_period_s</codeph> is set to 0, idle client connections
              stay open until explicitly closed by the clients.
            </p>

            <p>
              The connection will only be closed if all the associated sessions are idle or
              closed. Sessions cannot be idle unless either the flag
              <codeph>--idle_session_timeout</codeph> or the
              <codeph>IDLE_SESSION_TIMEOUT</codeph> query option is set to greater than 0. If
              idle session timeout is not configured, a session cannot become idle by
              definition, and therefore its connection stays open until the client explicitly
              closes it.
            </p>
          </dd>

        </dlentry>

        <dlentry>

          <dt>
            --max_cookie_lifetime_s
          </dt>

          <dd>
            Starting in Impala 3.4.0, Impala uses cookies for authentication when clients
            connect via HiveServer2 over HTTP. Use the <codeph>--max_cookie_lifetime_s</codeph>
            startup flag to control how long generated cookies are valid for.
            <p>
              Specify the value in seconds.
            </p>
            <p>
              The default value is 1 day.
            </p>

            <p>
              Setting the flag to <codeph>0</codeph> disables cookie support.
            </p>

            <p>
              When an unexpired cookie is successfully verified, the user name contained in the
              cookie is set on the connection.
            </p>

            <p>
              Each <codeph>impalad</codeph> uses its own key to generate the signature, so
              clients that reconnect to a different <codeph>impalad</codeph> have to
              re-authenticate.
            </p>

            <p>
              On a single <codeph>impalad</codeph>, cookies are valid across sessions and
              connections.
            </p>
          </dd>

        </dlentry>
      </dl>

    </section>

  </conbody>

</concept>
