<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept rev="1.2" id="delegation">

  <title>Configuring Impala Delegation for Hue and BI Tools</title>

  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <data name="Category" value="Security"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Impala"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Authentication"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Delegation"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Hue"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Administrators"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Developers"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Data Analysts"/>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>

  <conbody>

    <p>
<!--
      When users connect to Impala directly through the <cmdname>impala-shell</cmdname> interpreter, the Sentry
      authorization framework determines what actions they can take and what data they can see.
-->
      When users submit Impala queries through a separate application, such as Hue or a business intelligence tool,
      typically all requests are treated as coming from the same user. In Impala 1.2 and higher, authentication is
      extended by a new feature that allows applications to pass along credentials for the users that connect to
      them (known as <q>delegation</q>), and issue Impala queries with the privileges for those users. Currently,
      the delegation feature is available only for Impala queries submitted through application interfaces such as
      Hue and BI tools; for example, Impala cannot issue queries using the privileges of the HDFS user.
    </p>

    <p>
      The delegation feature is enabled by a startup option for <cmdname>impalad</cmdname>:
      <codeph>--authorized_proxy_user_config</codeph>. When you specify this option, users whose names you specify
      (such as <codeph>hue</codeph>) can delegate the execution of a query to another user. The query runs with the
      privileges of the delegated user, not the original user such as <codeph>hue</codeph>. The name of the
      delegated user is passed using the HiveServer2 configuration property <codeph>impala.doas.user</codeph>.
    </p>

    <p>
      You can specify a list of users that the application user can delegate to, or <codeph>*</codeph> to allow a
      superuser to delegate to any other user. For example:
    </p>

<codeblock>impalad --authorized_proxy_user_config 'hue=user1,user2;admin=*' ...</codeblock>

    <note>
      Make sure to use single quotes or escape characters to ensure that any <codeph>*</codeph> characters do not
      undergo wildcard expansion when specified in command-line arguments.
    </note>

    <p>
      See <xref href="impala_config_options.xml#config_options"/> for details about adding or changing
      <cmdname>impalad</cmdname> startup options. See
      <xref keyref="how-hiveserver2-brings-security-and-concurrency-to-apache-hive">this
      blog post</xref> for background information about the delegation capability in HiveServer2.
    </p>
    <p>
      To set up authentication for the delegated users:
    </p>

    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>
          On the server side, configure either user/password authentication through LDAP, or Kerberos
          authentication, for all the delegated users. See <xref href="impala_ldap.xml#ldap"/> or
          <xref href="impala_kerberos.xml#kerberos"/> for details.
        </p>
      </li>

      <li>
        <p>
          On the client side, to learn how to enable delegation, consult the documentation
          for the ODBC driver you are using.
        </p>
      </li>
    </ul>

  </conbody>

</concept>
