<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="impala_kudu" rev="kudu">

  <title>Using Impala to Query Kudu Tables</title>

  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <data name="Category" value="Impala"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Kudu"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Querying"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Data Analysts"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Developers"/>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>

  <conbody>

    <p>
      <indexterm audience="Cloudera">Kudu</indexterm>
      You can use Impala to query Kudu tables. This capability allows convenient access to a storage system that is
      tuned for different kinds of workloads than the default with Impala. The default Impala tables use data files
      stored on HDFS, which are ideal for bulk loads and queries using full-table scans. In contrast, Kudu can do
      efficient queries for data organized either in data warehouse style (with full table scans) or for OLTP-style
      workloads (with key-based lookups for single rows or small ranges of values).
    </p>

    <p>
      Certain Impala SQL statements, such as <codeph>UPDATE</codeph> and <codeph>DELETE</codeph>, only work with
      Kudu tables. These operations were impractical from a performance perspective to perform at large scale on
      HDFS data, or on HBase tables.
    </p>

  </conbody>

  <concept id="kudu_benefits">

    <title>Benefits of Using Kudu Tables with Impala</title>

    <conbody>

      <p>
        The combination of Kudu and Impala works best for tables where scan performance is important, but data
        arrives continuously, in small batches, or needs to be updated without being completely replaced. In these
        scenarios (such as for streaming data), it might be impractical to use Parquet tables because Parquet works
        best with multi-megabyte data files, requiring substantial overhead to replace or reorganize data files to
        accomodate frequent additions or changes to data. Impala can query Kudu tables with scan performance close
        to that of Parquet, and Impala can also perform update or delete operations without replacing the entire
        table contents. You can also use the Kudu API to do ingestion or transformation operations outside of
        Impala, and Impala can query the current data at any time.
      </p>

    </conbody>

  </concept>

  <concept id="kudu_primary_key">

    <title>Primary Key Columns for Kudu Tables</title>

    <conbody>

      <p>
        Kudu tables introduce the notion of primary keys to Impala for the first time. The primary key is made up
        of one or more columns, whose values are combined and used as a lookup key during queries. These columns
        cannot contain any <codeph>NULL</codeph> values or any duplicate values, and can never be updated. For a
        partitioned Kudu table, all the partition key columns must come from the set of primary key columns.
      </p>

      <p>
        Impala itself still does not have the notion of unique or non-<codeph>NULL</codeph> constraints. These
        restrictions on the primary key columns are enforced on the Kudu side.
      </p>

      <p>
        The primary key columns must be the first ones specified in the <codeph>CREATE TABLE</codeph> statement.
        You specify which column or columns make up the primary key in the table properties, rather than through
        attributes in the column list.
      </p>

      <p>
        Kudu can do extra optimizations for queries that refer to the primary key columns in the
        <codeph>WHERE</codeph> clause. It is not crucial though to include the primary key columns in the
        <codeph>WHERE</codeph> clause of every query. The benefit is mainly for partitioned tables,
        which divide the data among various tablet servers based on the distribution of
        data values in some or all of the primary key columns.
      </p>

    </conbody>

  </concept>

  <concept id="kudu_dml">

    <title>Impala DML Support for Kudu Tables</title>

    <conbody>

      <p>
        Impala supports certain DML statements for Kudu tables only. The <codeph>UPDATE</codeph> and
        <codeph>DELETE</codeph> statements let you modify data within Kudu tables without rewriting substantial
        amounts of table data.
      </p>

      <p>
        The <codeph>INSERT</codeph> statement for Kudu tables honors the unique and non-<codeph>NULL</codeph>
        requirements for the primary key columns.
      </p>

      <p>
        Because Impala and Kudu do not support transactions, the effects of any <codeph>INSERT</codeph>,
        <codeph>UPDATE</codeph>, or <codeph>DELETE</codeph> statement are immediately visible. For example, you
        cannot do a sequence of <codeph>UPDATE</codeph> statements and only make the change visible after all the
        statements are finished. Also, if a DML statement fails partway through, any rows that were already
        inserted, deleted, or changed remain in the table; there is no rollback mechanism to undo the changes.
      </p>

    </conbody>

  </concept>

  <concept id="kudu_partitioning">

    <title>Partitioning for Kudu Tables</title>

    <conbody>

      <p>
        Kudu tables use special mechanisms to evenly distribute data among the underlying tablet servers. Although
        we refer to such tables as partitioned tables, they are distinguished from traditional Impala partitioned
        tables by use of different clauses on the <codeph>CREATE TABLE</codeph> statement. Partitioned Kudu tables
        use <codeph>PARTITION BY</codeph>, <codeph>HASH</codeph>, and <codeph>RANGE</codeph> clauses rather than
        the traditional <codeph>PARTITIONED BY</codeph> clause. All of the columns involved in these clauses must
        be primary key columns. These clauses let you specify different ways to divide the data for each column,
        or even for different value ranges within a column. This flexibility lets you avoid problems with uneven
        distribution of data, where the partitioning scheme for HDFS tables might result in some partitions being
        much larger than others. By setting up an effective partitioning scheme for a Kudu table, you can ensure
        that the work for a query can be parallelized evenly across the hosts in a cluster.
      </p>

    </conbody>

  </concept>

  <concept id="kudu_performance">

    <title>Impala Query Performance for Kudu Tables</title>

    <conbody>

      <p>
        For queries involving Kudu tables, Impala can delegate much of the work of filtering the result set to
        Kudu, avoiding some of the I/O involved in full table scans of tables containing HDFS data files. This type
        of optimization is especially effective for partitioned Kudu tables, where the Impala query
        <codeph>WHERE</codeph> clause refers to one or more primary key columns that are also used as partition key
        columns. For example, if a partitioned Kudu table uses a <codeph>HASH</codeph> clause for
        <codeph>col1</codeph> and a <codeph>RANGE</codeph> clause for <codeph>col2</codeph>, a query using a clause
        such as <codeph>WHERE col1 IN (1,2,3) AND col2 &gt; 100</codeph> can determine exactly which tablet servers
        contain relevant data, and therefore parallelize the query very efficiently.
      </p>

    </conbody>

  </concept>

</concept>
