<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="cm_installation">

  <title>Installing Impala with Cloudera Manager</title>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <data name="Category" value="Impala"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Installing"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Cloudera Manager"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Administrators"/>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>

  <conbody>

    <p>
      Before installing Impala through the Cloudera Manager interface, make sure all applicable nodes have the
      appropriate hardware configuration and levels of operating system and CDH. See
      <xref href="impala_prereqs.xml#prereqs"/> for details.
    </p>

    <note rev="1.2.0">
      <p rev="1.2.0">
        To install the latest Impala under CDH 4, upgrade Cloudera Manager to 4.8 or higher. Cloudera Manager 4.8 is
        the first release that can manage the Impala catalog service introduced in Impala 1.2. Cloudera Manager 4.8
        requires this service to be present, so if you upgrade to Cloudera Manager 4.8, also upgrade Impala to the
        most recent version at the same time.
<!-- Not so relevant now for 1.1.1, but maybe someday we'll capture all this history in a compatibility grid.
        Upgrade to Cloudera Manager 4.6.2 or higher to enable Cloudera Manager to
        handle access control for the Impala web UI, available by default through
        port 25000 on each Impala host.
        -->
      </p>
    </note>

    <p>
      For information on installing Impala in a Cloudera Manager-managed environment, see
      <xref audience="integrated" href="cm_ig_install_impala.xml"/><xref audience="standalone" href="http://www.cloudera.com/documentation/enterprise/latest/topics/cm_ig_install_impala.html" scope="external" format="html">Installing Impala</xref>.
    </p>

    <p>
      Managing your Impala installation through Cloudera Manager has a number of advantages. For example, when you
      make configuration changes to CDH components using Cloudera Manager, it automatically applies changes to the
      copies of configuration files, such as <codeph>hive-site.xml</codeph>, that Impala keeps under
      <filepath>/etc/impala/conf</filepath>. It also sets up the Hive Metastore service that is required for
      Impala running under CDH 4.1.
    </p>

    <p>
      In some cases, depending on the level of Impala, CDH, and Cloudera Manager, you might need to add particular
      component configuration details in some of the free-form option fields on the Impala configuration pages
      within Cloudera Manager. <ph conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/safety_valve"/>
    </p>
  </conbody>
</concept>
