<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="impala_opentelemetry_support" rev="5.0">
  <title>OpenTelemetry support for Impala</title>
  <titlealts audience="PDF">
    <navtitle>OpenTelemetry support</navtitle>
  </titlealts>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <data name="Category" value="Impala"/>
      <data name="Category" value="OpenTelemetry"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Observability"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Data Management"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Administrators"/>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>
  <conbody>
    <p>Impala telemetry data is integrated with OTel-compatible collectors. This provides a
      centralized flow of live query insights, with <codeph>SELECT</codeph> queries, DMLs, and DDLs
      represented as OTel traces, and reduces the friction of sourcing data from multiple places.
      See <xref href="https://opentelemetry.io/" format="html" scope="external">OpenTelemetry
        (OTel)</xref> for more information.</p>
    <section>
      <title>Impala integration with OTel</title>
      <p>Impala integrates the OTel C++ SDK to emit query lifecycle data as OpenTelemetry traces.
        The system already tracks specific phases and events for each query and records them in the
        query profile timeline section. By emitting these events to an OTel collector, observability
        systems can track active queries in near real-time.</p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Collected telemetry data</title>
      <p>Telemetry data emitted from Impala carries crucial information that is currently available
        only in the query profile and workload management tables. Telemetry data includes the
        following data:<ol>
          <li>The initiating user</li>
          <li>The SQL statement</li>
          <li>Memory estimates and actual use</li>
          <li>Other important data related to the query lifecycle</li>
        </ol></p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Benefits of OTel Impala Integration</title>
      <dl>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Enhanced query lifecycle and historical data</dt>
          <dd>Integrating OTel with Impala provides enhanced observability through comprehensive
            data collection. The following data is collected:<ul>
              <li>Live query data – Data about important events in the lifecycle of actively running
                queries is sent to collectors in near real-time as the events happen.</li>
              <li>Historical query data – Data about completed queries can be retained by the
                destination OTel trace management system.</li>
            </ul></dd>
        </dlentry>
      </dl>
      <dl>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Performance and scalability impact</dt>
          <dd>The integration is designed to have negligible impact on Impala's performance and is
            built for scalability. The following performance and scalability impacts are valid for
            the integration:<ul>
              <li>The performance impact on Impala is negligible because the system already collects
                all the necessary event and metric data.</li>
              <li>The process of sending data to the OTel endpoint is handled out-of-band in a
                separate thread, limiting any additional resource usage to just the sending of this
                data.</li>
              <li>Scalability concerns are primarily limited to the OTel Collector endpoint. Impala
                does not encounter scalability issues as long as communication with the Collector
                happens without delay.</li>
            </ul></dd>
        </dlentry>
      </dl>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>OpenTelemetry Impala query tracing example</title>
      <p>
        <note type="important">The example backend systems shown here are just for representation.
          Along with having your own instance of the OTel collector, you must also have your own
          instances of Jaeger, Zipkin, or other trace visualization system to view the telemetry data.</note>
      </p>
      <p>After configuring OpenTelemetry support for your Impala, you can view detailed telemetry
        data for your queries in a trace visualization system like Jaeger. The following steps show
        a typical workflow for finding and analyzing a query trace.</p>
      <dl>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Finding a query trace</dt>
          <dd>
            <ol>
              <li>On the Jaeger UI, use the search function to find traces. You can filter by
                service, such as Impalad, or other tags like the query ID. The search results
                provide a high-level summary of the traces found.</li>
              <li>From the search results, select a specific trace to view its summary and
                timeline.</li>
            </ol>
          </dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Understanding the query trace timeline</dt>
          <dd>A trace provides a detailed breakdown of a query execution from start to finish. Each
            segment in the timeline is a span, representing a specific operation. The main query is
            represented by a root span, and its various stages are shown as child spans.</dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Analyzing child spans</dt>
          <dd>By inspecting the individual child spans, you can gain deep insights into the
            performance of each stage of the query. For example, you can see how much time was spent
            on planning, admission control, and execution.<p>The following query stages are shown in
              the child spans:<ol>
                <li>Query initialization – This span is generated immediately when a query is
                  received to capture the initial setup and is useful for checking early details,
                  such as the user and query ID.</li>
                <li>Query planning – This span shows the time taken to plan the query. A long
                  duration here might indicate a complex query or metadata-related issues.</li>
                <li>Admission control – This span records the time spent waiting for resources. A
                  long duration here suggests high resource contention.</li>
                <li>Query execution – This span represents the time for the actual query to run.
                  This is a crucial metric for evaluating performance.</li>
                <li>Query close – This span marks the end of the query lifecycle, including cleanup
                  and final reporting.</li>
                <li>Failed query – A failed query will also generate a trace that can be analyzed to
                  understand the cause of the failure.</li>
              </ol></p><p>Analyzing these spans helps you identify performance bottlenecks and
              understand the entire lifecycle of a query within your Impala.</p></dd>
        </dlentry>
      </dl>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Enabling OpenTelemetry tracing in the Impala Coordinator</title>
      <p>To enable OpenTelemetry (OTel) tracing for monitoring and diagnostics in your Impala
        cluster, add the appropriate startup flags to your Impala Coordinator nodes.<ol>
          <li>Configure the required flags - Restart your Impala Coordinator instances with the
            following mandatory flags to activate tracing:<ul>
              <li><codeph>--otel_trace_enabled</codeph>- Set to <codeph>true</codeph> to generate
                and export OpenTelemetry traces. (Default: <codeph>false</codeph>)</li>
              <li><codeph>--otel_trace_collector_url</codeph>- Specifies the valid URL endpoint of
                the OpenTelemetry collector where trace data is
                exported.<codeblock>--otel_trace_collector_url=https://collector-endpoint</codeblock></li>
            </ul></li>
          <li>Configure optional performance and network tuning flags (Optional) - You can append
            any of the following optional configuration keys to fine-tune batch sizing, timeouts, or
            connection behaviors:<ul>
              <li><codeph>--otel_trace_batch_max_batch_size</codeph>- Maximum batch size for each
                export to the OTel Collector. (Default: <codeph>512</codeph>)</li>
              <li><codeph>--otel_trace_batch_queue_size</codeph>- Maximum buffer or queue size.
                Spans are dropped after this limit is reached. (Default: <codeph>2048</codeph>)</li>
              <li><codeph>--otel_trace_batch_schedule_delay_ms</codeph>- Delay interval in
                milliseconds between consecutive batch exports. (Default:
                <codeph>5000</codeph>)</li>
              <li><codeph>--otel_trace_compression</codeph>- Uses ZLib compression when sending data
                to the OTel Collector. (Default: <codeph>true</codeph>)</li>
              <li><codeph>--otel_trace_timeout_s</codeph>- Export timeout threshold in seconds.
                (Default: <codeph>10</codeph>)</li>
              <li><codeph>--otel_debug</codeph>- Set to <codeph>true</codeph> to output additional
                telemetry debug logs. (Default: <codeph>false</codeph>)</li>
            </ul></li>
        </ol></p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Limitations</title>
      <p>The current OpenTelemetry integration for Impala has the following limitations:<dl
          id="dl_uzw_kfw_lgc">
          <dlentry>
            <dt>Telemetry data scope</dt>
            <dd>The scope of telemetry data is currently limited to only traces of select queries,
              DMLs, and DDLs. Other types of data such as metrics or logs will not be handled in the
              initial release. However, the design is prepared to allow metrics or logs to be added
              in the future without significant architectural changes.</dd>
          </dlentry>
          <dlentry>
            <dt>Fixed trace data</dt>
            <dd>The traces being sent from Impala are not configurable. This means you cannot
              customize the specific data points included in the traces.</dd>
          </dlentry>
        </dl></p>
    </section>
  </conbody>
</concept>
