<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="proxy">

  <title>Using Impala through a Proxy for High Availability</title>
  <titlealts audience="PDF"><navtitle>Load-Balancing Proxy for HA</navtitle></titlealts>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <data name="Category" value="High Availability"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Impala"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Network"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Proxy"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Administrators"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Developers"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Data Analysts"/>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>

  <conbody>

    <p>
      For most clusters that have multiple users and production availability requirements, you might set up a proxy
      server to relay requests to and from Impala.
    </p>

    <p>
      Currently, the Impala statestore mechanism does not include such proxying and load-balancing features. Set up
      a software package of your choice to perform these functions.
    </p>

    <note>
      <p conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/statestored_catalogd_ha_blurb"/>
    </note>

    <p outputclass="toc inpage"/>

  </conbody>

  <concept id="proxy_overview">

    <title>Overview of Proxy Usage and Load Balancing for Impala</title>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <data name="Category" value="Concepts"/>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>

    <conbody>

      <p>
        Using a load-balancing proxy server for Impala has the following advantages:
      </p>

      <ul>
        <li>
          Applications connect to a single well-known host and port, rather than keeping track of the hosts where
          the <cmdname>impalad</cmdname> daemon is running.
        </li>

        <li>
          If any host running the <cmdname>impalad</cmdname> daemon becomes unavailable, application connection
          requests still succeed because you always connect to the proxy server rather than a specific host running
          the <cmdname>impalad</cmdname> daemon.
        </li>

        <li>
          The coordinator node for each Impala query potentially requires more memory and CPU cycles than the other
          nodes that process the query. The proxy server can issue queries using round-robin scheduling, so that
          each connection uses a different coordinator node. This load-balancing technique lets the Impala nodes
          share this additional work, rather than concentrating it on a single machine.
        </li>
      </ul>

      <p>
        The following setup steps are a general outline that apply to any load-balancing proxy software:
      </p>

      <ol>
        <li>
          Download the load-balancing proxy software. It should only need to be installed and configured on a
          single host. Pick a host other than the DataNodes where <cmdname>impalad</cmdname> is running,
          because the intention is to protect against the possibility of one or more of these DataNodes becoming unavailable.
        </li>

        <li>
          Configure the load balancer (typically by editing a configuration file).
          In particular:
          <ul>
            <li>
              <p>
                Set up a port that the load balancer will listen on to relay Impala requests back and forth.
              </p>
            </li>
            <li>
              <p rev="DOCS-690">
                Consider enabling <q>sticky sessions</q>. Where practical, enable this setting
                so that stateless client applications such as <cmdname>impalad</cmdname> and Hue
                are not disconnected from long-running queries. Evaluate whether this setting is
                appropriate for your combination of workload and client applications.
              </p>
            </li>
            <li>
              <p>
                For Kerberized clusters, follow the instructions in <xref href="impala_proxy.xml#proxy_kerberos"/>.
              </p>
            </li>
          </ul>
        </li>

        <li>
          Specify the host and port settings for each Impala node. These are the hosts that the load balancer will
          choose from when relaying each Impala query. See <xref href="impala_ports.xml#ports"/> for when to use
          port 21000, 21050, or another value depending on what type of connections you are load balancing.
          <note rev="">
            <p rev="">
              In particular, if you are using Hue or JDBC-based applications,
              you typically set up load balancing for both ports 21000 and 21050, because
              these client applications connect through port 21050 while the <cmdname>impala-shell</cmdname>
              command connects through port 21000.
            </p>
          </note>
        </li>

        <li>
          Run the load-balancing proxy server, pointing it at the configuration file that you set up.
        </li>

        <li>
          For any scripts, jobs, or configuration settings for applications that formerly connected to a specific
          datanode to run Impala SQL statements, change the connection information (such as the <codeph>-i</codeph>
          option in <cmdname>impala-shell</cmdname>) to point to the load balancer instead.
        </li>
      </ol>

      <note>
        The following sections use the HAProxy software as a representative example of a load balancer
        that you can use with Impala.
      </note>

    </conbody>

  </concept>

  <concept id="proxy_balancing" rev="" audience="hidden">
    <title>Choosing the Load-Balancing Algorithm</title>
    <conbody>
      <p>
        Load-balancing software offers a number of algorithms to distribute requests.
        Each algorithm has its own characteristics that make it suitable in some situations
        but not others.
      </p>

      <dl>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>leastconn</dt>
          <dd>
            Connects sessions to the coordinator with the fewest connections, to balance the load evenly.
            Typically used for workloads consisting of many independent, short-running queries.
            In configurations with only a few client machines, this setting can avoid having all
            requests go to only a small set of coordinators.
          </dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>source affinity</dt>
          <dd>
            Sessions from the same IP address always go to the same coordinator.
            A good choice for Impala workloads containing a mix of queries and
            DDL statements, such as <codeph>CREATE TABLE</codeph> and <codeph>ALTER TABLE</codeph>.
            Because the metadata changes from a DDL statement take time to propagate across the cluster,
            prefer to use source affinity in this case. If necessary, run the DDL and subsequent
            queries that depend on the results of the DDL through the same session, for example
            by running <codeph>impala-shell -f <varname>script_file</varname></codeph> to submit
            several statements through a single session.
            An alternative is to set the query option <codeph>SYNC_DDL=1</codeph>
            to hold back subsequent queries until the results of a DDL operation have propagated
            throughout the cluster, but that is a relatively expensive setting.
            Recommended for use with Hue.
          </dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>sticky</dt>
          <dd>
            Similar to source affinity. Sessions from the same IP address always go to the same coordinator.
            The maintenance overhead for the <q>stick tables</q> can cause long-running Hue sessions
            to disconnect, therefore source affinity is often a better choice.
          </dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>round-robin</dt>
          <dd>
            Distributes connections to all coordinator nodes.
            Typically not recommended for Impala.
          </dd>
        </dlentry>
      </dl>

      <p>
        You might need to perform benchmarks and load testing to determine which setting is optimal for your
        use case. If some client applications have special characteristics, such as long-running Hue queries
        working best with source affinity, you might configure multiple virtual IP addresses with a
        different load-balancing algorithm for each.
      </p>

    </conbody>
  </concept>

  <concept id="proxy_kerberos">

    <title>Special Proxy Considerations for Clusters Using Kerberos</title>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <data name="Category" value="Security"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Kerberos"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Authentication"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Proxy"/>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>

    <conbody>

      <p>
        In a cluster using Kerberos, applications check host credentials to
        verify that the host they are connecting to is the same one that is
        actually processing the request, to prevent man-in-the-middle attacks.
      </p>
      <note>
          Once you enable a proxy server in a Kerberized cluster, users will not
          be able to connect to individual impala daemons directly from impala
          shell.
      </note>
      <p>
        To clarify that the load-balancing proxy server is legitimate, perform
        these extra Kerberos setup steps:
      </p>

      <ol>
        <li>
          This section assumes you are starting with a Kerberos-enabled cluster. See
          <xref href="impala_kerberos.xml#kerberos"/> for instructions for setting up Impala with Kerberos. See
          <xref keyref="cdh_sg_kerberos_prin_keytab_deploy"/> for general steps to set up Kerberos.
        </li>

        <li>
          Choose the host you will use for the proxy server. Based on the Kerberos setup procedure, it should
          already have an entry <codeph>impala/<varname>proxy_host</varname>@<varname>realm</varname></codeph> in
          its keytab. If not, go back over the initial Kerberos configuration steps for the keytab on each host
          running the <cmdname>impalad</cmdname> daemon.
        </li>

        <li>
          Copy the keytab file from the proxy host to all other hosts in the cluster that run the
          <cmdname>impalad</cmdname> daemon. (For optimal performance, <cmdname>impalad</cmdname> should be running
          on all DataNodes in the cluster.) Put the keytab file in a secure location on each of these other hosts.
        </li>

        <li>
          Add an entry <codeph>impala/<varname>actual_hostname</varname>@<varname>realm</varname></codeph> to the keytab on each
          host running the <cmdname>impalad</cmdname> daemon.
        </li>

        <li>

         For each impalad node, merge the existing keytab with the proxy’s keytab using
          <cmdname>ktutil</cmdname>, producing a new keytab file. For example:
          <codeblock>$ ktutil
  ktutil: read_kt proxy.keytab
  ktutil: read_kt impala.keytab
  ktutil: write_kt proxy_impala.keytab
  ktutil: quit</codeblock>

        </li>

        <li>

          To verify that the keytabs are merged, run the command:
<codeblock>
klist -k <varname>keytabfile</varname>
</codeblock>
          which lists the credentials for both <codeph>principal</codeph> and <codeph>be_principal</codeph> on
          all nodes.
        </li>


        <li>

          Make sure that the <codeph>impala</codeph> user has permission to read this merged keytab file.

        </li>

        <li>
          Change the following configuration settings for each host in the cluster that participates
          in the load balancing:
          <ul>
            <li>
              In the <cmdname>impalad</cmdname> option definition, add:
<codeblock>
--principal=impala/<i>proxy_host@realm</i>
  --be_principal=impala/<i>actual_host@realm</i>
  --keytab_file=<i>path_to_merged_keytab</i>
</codeblock>
              <note>
                Every host has different <codeph>--be_principal</codeph> because the actual hostname
                is different on each host.

                Specify the fully qualified domain name (FQDN) for the proxy host, not the IP
                address. Use the exact FQDN as returned by a reverse DNS lookup for the associated
                IP address.

              </note>
            </li>

            <li>
              Modify the startup options. See <xref href="impala_config_options.xml#config_options"/> for the procedure to modify the startup
              options.
            </li>
          </ul>
        </li>

        <li>
          Restart Impala to make the changes take effect. Restart the <cmdname>impalad</cmdname> daemons on all
          hosts in the cluster, as well as the <cmdname>statestored</cmdname> and <cmdname>catalogd</cmdname>
          daemons.
        </li>

      </ol>

<!--
We basically want to merge the keytab from the proxy host to all the impalad host's keytab file. To merge two keytab files, we first need to ship the proxy keytab to all the impalad node, then merge keytab files using MIT Kerberos "ktutil" command line tool.

<codeblock>$ ktutil
ktutil: read_kt krb5.keytab
ktutil: read_kt proxy-host.keytab
ktutil: write_kt krb5.keytab
ktutil: quit</codeblock>

The setup of the -principal and -be_principal has to be set through safety valve.
-->

    </conbody>

  </concept>

  <concept id="tut_proxy">

    <title>Example of Configuring HAProxy Load Balancer for Impala</title>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <data name="Category" value="Configuring"/>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>

    <conbody>

      <p>
        If you are not already using a load-balancing proxy, you can experiment with
        <xref href="http://haproxy.1wt.eu/" scope="external" format="html">HAProxy</xref> a free, open source load
        balancer. This example shows how you might install and configure that load balancer on a Red Hat Enterprise
        Linux system.
      </p>

      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>
            Install the load balancer: <codeph>yum install haproxy</codeph>
          </p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <p>
            Set up the configuration file: <filepath>/etc/haproxy/haproxy.cfg</filepath>. See the following section
            for a sample configuration file.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <p>
            Run the load balancer (on a single host, preferably one not running <cmdname>impalad</cmdname>):
          </p>
<codeblock>/usr/sbin/haproxy –f /etc/haproxy/haproxy.cfg</codeblock>
        </li>

        <li>
          <p>
            In <cmdname>impala-shell</cmdname>, JDBC applications, or ODBC applications, connect to the listener
            port of the proxy host, rather than port 21000 or 21050 on a host actually running <cmdname>impalad</cmdname>.
            The sample configuration file sets haproxy to listen on port 25003, therefore you would send all
            requests to <codeph><varname>haproxy_host</varname>:25003</codeph>.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ul>

      <p>
        This is the sample <filepath>haproxy.cfg</filepath> used in this example:
      </p>

<codeblock>global
    # To have these messages end up in /var/log/haproxy.log you will
    # need to:
    #
    # 1) configure syslog to accept network log events.  This is done
    #    by adding the '-r' option to the SYSLOGD_OPTIONS in
    #    /etc/sysconfig/syslog
    #
    # 2) configure local2 events to go to the /var/log/haproxy.log
    #   file. A line like the following can be added to
    #   /etc/sysconfig/syslog
    #
    #    local2.*                       /var/log/haproxy.log
    #
    log         127.0.0.1 local0
    log         127.0.0.1 local1 notice
    chroot      /var/lib/haproxy
    pidfile     /var/run/haproxy.pid
    maxconn     4000
    user        haproxy
    group       haproxy
    daemon

    # turn on stats unix socket
    #stats socket /var/lib/haproxy/stats

#---------------------------------------------------------------------
# common defaults that all the 'listen' and 'backend' sections will
# use if not designated in their block
#
# You might need to adjust timing values to prevent timeouts.
#---------------------------------------------------------------------
defaults
    mode                    http
    log                     global
    option                  httplog
    option                  dontlognull
    option http-server-close
    option forwardfor       except 127.0.0.0/8
    option                  redispatch
    retries                 3
    maxconn                 3000
    contimeout 5000
    clitimeout 50000
    srvtimeout 50000

#
# This sets up the admin page for HA Proxy at port 25002.
#
listen stats :25002
    balance
    mode http
    stats enable
    stats auth <varname>username</varname>:<varname>password</varname>

# This is the setup for Impala. Impala client connect to load_balancer_host:25003.
# HAProxy will balance connections among the list of servers listed below.
# The list of Impalad is listening at port 21000 for beeswax (impala-shell) or original ODBC driver.
# For JDBC or ODBC version 2.x driver, use port 21050 instead of 21000.
listen impala :25003
    mode tcp
    option tcplog
    balance leastconn

    server <varname>symbolic_name_1</varname> impala-host-1.example.com:21000
    server <varname>symbolic_name_2</varname> impala-host-2.example.com:21000
    server <varname>symbolic_name_3</varname> impala-host-3.example.com:21000
    server <varname>symbolic_name_4</varname> impala-host-4.example.com:21000

# Setup for Hue or other JDBC-enabled applications.
# In particular, Hue requires sticky sessions.
# The application connects to load_balancer_host:21051, and HAProxy balances
# connections to the associated hosts, where Impala listens for JDBC
# requests on port 21050.
listen impalajdbc :21051
    mode tcp
    option tcplog
    balance source
    server <varname>symbolic_name_5</varname> impala-host-1.example.com:21050
    server <varname>symbolic_name_6</varname> impala-host-2.example.com:21050
    server <varname>symbolic_name_7</varname> impala-host-3.example.com:21050
    server <varname>symbolic_name_8</varname> impala-host-4.example.com:21050
</codeblock>

      <note conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/proxy_jdbc_caveat"/>

    </conbody>

  </concept>

</concept>
