<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="file_formats">

  <title>How Impala Works with Hadoop File Formats</title>

  <titlealts audience="PDF">

    <navtitle>File Formats</navtitle>

  </titlealts>

  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <data name="Category" value="Impala"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Concepts"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Hadoop"/>
      <data name="Category" value="File Formats"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Developers"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Data Analysts"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Stub Pages"/>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>

  <conbody>

    <p>
      Impala supports several familiar file formats used in Apache Hadoop. Impala can load and
      query data files produced by other Hadoop components such as Spark, and data files
      produced by Impala can be used by other components also. The following sections discuss
      the procedures, limitations, and performance considerations for using each file format
      with Impala.
    </p>

    <p>
      The file format used for an Impala table has significant performance consequences. Some
      file formats include compression support that affects the size of data on the disk and,
      consequently, the amount of I/O and CPU resources required to deserialize data. The
      amounts of I/O and CPU resources required can be a limiting factor in query performance
      since querying often begins with moving and decompressing data. To reduce the potential
      impact of this part of the process, data is often compressed. By compressing data, a
      smaller total number of bytes are transferred from disk to memory. This reduces the amount
      of time taken to transfer the data, but a tradeoff occurs when the CPU decompresses the
      content.
    </p>

    <p>
      For the file formats that Impala cannot write to, create the table from within Impala
      whenever possible and insert data using another component such as Hive or Spark. See the
      table below for specific file formats.
    </p>

    <p>
      The following table lists the file formats that Impala supports.
    </p>

    <table>
      <tgroup cols="5">
        <colspec colname="1" colwidth="10*"/>
        <colspec colname="2" colwidth="10*"/>
        <colspec colname="3" colwidth="20*"/>
        <colspec colname="4" colwidth="30*"/>
        <colspec colname="5" colwidth="30*"/>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>
              File Type
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Format
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Compression Codecs
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Impala Can CREATE?
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Impala Can INSERT?
            </entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row id="parquet_support">
            <entry>
              <xref href="impala_parquet.xml#parquet">Parquet</xref>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Structured
            </entry>
            <entry>Snappy, gzip, zstd, lz4; currently Snappy by default </entry>
            <entry>
              Yes.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Yes: <codeph>CREATE TABLE</codeph>, <codeph>INSERT</codeph>, <codeph>LOAD
              DATA</codeph>, and query.
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row id="orc_support">
            <entry>
              <xref href="impala_orc.xml#orc">ORC</xref>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Structured
            </entry>
            <entry>
              gzip, Snappy, LZO, LZ4; currently gzip by default
            </entry>
            <entry> Yes, in Impala 2.12.0 and higher. <p>By default, ORC reads are enabled in Impala
              3.4.0 and higher. </p>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              No. Import data by using <codeph>LOAD DATA</codeph> on data files already in the
              right format, or use <codeph>INSERT</codeph> in Hive followed by <codeph>REFRESH
              <varname>table_name</varname></codeph> in Impala.
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row id="txtfile_support">
            <entry>
              <xref href="impala_txtfile.xml#txtfile">Text</xref>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Unstructured
            </entry>
            <entry rev="2.0.0">bzip2, deflate, gzip, LZO, Snappy, zstd</entry>
            <entry>
              Yes. For <codeph>CREATE TABLE</codeph> with no <codeph>STORED AS</codeph> clause,
              the default file format is uncompressed text, with values separated by ASCII
              <codeph>0x01</codeph> characters (typically represented as Ctrl-A).
            </entry>
            <entry> Yes if uncompressed.<p>No if compressed.</p><p>If LZO
                compression is used, you must create the table and load data in
                Hive.</p><p>If other kinds of compression are used, you must
                load data through <codeph>LOAD DATA</codeph>, Hive, or manually
                in HDFS. </p></entry>
          </row>
          <row id="avro_support">
            <entry>
              <xref href="impala_avro.xml#avro">Avro</xref>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Structured
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Snappy, gzip, deflate
            </entry>
            <entry rev="1.4.0">
              Yes, in Impala 1.4.0 and higher. In lower versions, create the table using Hive.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              No. Import data by using <codeph>LOAD DATA</codeph> on data files already in the
              right format, or use <codeph>INSERT</codeph> in Hive followed by <codeph>REFRESH
              <varname>table_name</varname></codeph> in Impala.
            </entry>
<!-- <entry rev="2.0.0">Yes, in Impala 2.0 and higher. For earlier Impala releases, load data through <codeph>LOAD DATA</codeph> on data files already in the right format, or use <codeph>INSERT</codeph> in Hive.</entry> -->
          </row>
          <row id="hudi_support">
            <entry>
              <xref href="impala_hudi.xml#hudi">Hudi</xref>
            </entry>
            <entry>Structured</entry>
            <entry>Snappy, gzip, zstd, lz4; currently Snappy by default </entry>
            <entry>Yes, support for Read Optimized Queries is experimental.</entry>
            <entry>No. Create an external table in Impala. Set the table location to the Hudi table
              directory. Alternatively, create the Hudi table in Hive. </entry>
          </row>
          <row id="rcfile_support">
            <entry>
              <xref href="impala_rcfile.xml#rcfile">RCFile</xref>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Structured
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Snappy, gzip, deflate, bzip2
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Yes.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              No. Import data by using <codeph>LOAD DATA</codeph> on data files already in the
              right format, or use <codeph>INSERT</codeph> in Hive followed by <codeph>REFRESH
              <varname>table_name</varname></codeph> in Impala.
            </entry>
<!--
            <entry rev="2.0.0">Yes, in Impala 2.0 and higher. For earlier Impala releases, load data through <codeph>LOAD DATA</codeph> on data files already in the right format, or use <codeph>INSERT</codeph> in Hive.</entry>
            -->
          </row>
          <row id="sequencefile_support">
            <entry>
              <xref href="impala_seqfile.xml#seqfile">SequenceFile</xref>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Structured
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Snappy, gzip, deflate, bzip2
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Yes.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              No. Import data by using <codeph>LOAD DATA</codeph> on data files already in the
              right format, or use <codeph>INSERT</codeph> in Hive followed by <codeph>REFRESH
              <varname>table_name</varname></codeph> in Impala.
            </entry>
<!--
            <entry rev="2.0.0">
              Yes, in Impala 2.0 and higher. For earlier Impala releases, load data through <codeph>LOAD
              DATA</codeph> on data files already in the right format, or use <codeph>INSERT</codeph> in Hive.
            </entry>
-->
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <p>
      Impala supports the following compression codecs:
    </p>

    <dl>
      <dlentry rev="2.0.0">

        <dt>
          Snappy
        </dt>

        <dd>
          <p>
            Recommended for its effective balance between compression ratio and decompression
            speed. Snappy compression is very fast, but gzip provides greater space savings.
            Supported for text, RC, Sequence, and Avro files in Impala 2.0 and higher.
          </p>
        </dd>

      </dlentry>

      <dlentry rev="2.0.0">

        <dt>
          Gzip
        </dt>

        <dd>
          <p>
            Recommended when achieving the highest level of compression (and therefore greatest
            disk-space savings) is desired. Supported for text, RC, Sequence and Avro files in
            Impala 2.0 and higher.
          </p>
        </dd>

      </dlentry>

      <dlentry rev="2.0.0">

        <dt>
          Deflate
        </dt>

        <dd>
          <p> Supported for AVRO, RC, Sequence, and text files. </p>
        </dd>

      </dlentry>

      <dlentry rev="2.0.0">

        <dt>
          Bzip2
        </dt>

        <dd>
          <p>
            Supported for text, RC, and Sequence files in Impala 2.0 and higher.
          </p>
        </dd>

      </dlentry>

      <dlentry rev="2.0.0">

        <dt>
          LZO
        </dt>

        <dd>
          <p>
            For text files only. Impala can query LZO-compressed text tables, but currently
            cannot create them or insert data into them. You need to perform these operations in
            Hive.
          </p>
        </dd>

      </dlentry>
      <dlentry>
        <dt>Zstd</dt>
        <dd>For Parquet and text files only.</dd>
      </dlentry>

      <dlentry>
        <dt>Lz4</dt>
        <dd>For Parquet files only.</dd>
      </dlentry>
    </dl>

  </conbody>

  <concept id="file_format_choosing">

    <title>Choosing the File Format for a Table</title>

    <prolog>
      <metadata>
        <data name="Category" value="Planning"/>
      </metadata>
    </prolog>

    <conbody>

      <p>
        Different file formats and compression codecs work better for different data sets.
        Choosing the proper format for your data can yield performance improvements. Use the
        following considerations to decide which combination of file format and compression to
        use for a particular table:
      </p>

      <ul>
        <li>
          If you are working with existing files that are already in a supported file format,
          use the same format for the Impala table if performance is acceptable. If the original
          format does not yield acceptable query performance or resource usage, consider
          creating a new Impala table with different file format or compression characteristics,
          and doing a one-time conversion by rewriting the data to the new table.
        </li>

        <li>
          Text files are convenient to produce through many different tools, and are
          human-readable for ease of verification and debugging. Those characteristics are why
          text is the default format for an Impala <codeph>CREATE TABLE</codeph> statement.
          However, when performance and resource usage are the primary considerations, use one
          of the structured file formats that include metadata and built-in compression.
          <p>
            A typical workflow might involve bringing data into an Impala table by copying CSV
            or TSV files into the appropriate data directory, and then using the <codeph>INSERT
            ... SELECT</codeph> syntax to rewrite the data into a table using a different, more
            compact file format.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ul>

    </conbody>

  </concept>

</concept>
