<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="impala_odbc">

  <title id="odbc">Configuring Impala to Work with ODBC</title>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <data name="Category" value="Impala"/>
      <data name="Category" value="ODBC"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Querying"/>
      <data name="Category" value="SQL"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Configuring"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Developers"/>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>

  <conbody>

    <p>
      <indexterm audience="Cloudera">ODBC</indexterm>
      Third-party products can be designed to integrate with Impala using ODBC. For the best experience, ensure any
      third-party product you intend to use is supported. Verifying support includes checking that the versions of
      Impala, ODBC, the operating system, and the third-party product have all been approved for use together.
      Before configuring your systems to use ODBC, download a connector.
      You may need to sign in and accept license agreements before accessing the pages required for downloading
      ODBC connectors.
    </p>

    <p outputclass="toc inpage"/>

  </conbody>

  <concept id="odbc_driver">
    <title>Downloading the ODBC Driver</title>
      <conbody>

      <note type="important">
        As of late 2015, most business intelligence applications are certified with the 2.x ODBC drivers.
        Although the instructions on this page cover both the 2.x and 1.x drivers, expect to use the 2.x drivers
        exclusively for most ODBC applications connecting to Impala.
      </note>

        <p>
          See the
          <xref href="http://www.cloudera.com/content/support/en/downloads/download-components/download-products.html?productID=3mDesWddUS" scope="external" format="html">downloads
          page</xref> for a matrix of the certified driver version for different products. See the
          <xref href="http://www.cloudera.com/content/support/en/documentation/cloudera-connectors-documentation/connector-documentation-latest.html" scope="external" format="html">documentation
          page</xref> for installation instructions.
        </p>

      </conbody>
    </concept>

    <concept id="odbc_port">
      <title>Configuring the ODBC Port</title>
      <conbody>
        <p>
          Versions 2.5 and 2.0 of the Cloudera ODBC Connector, currently certified for some but not all BI applications,
          use the HiveServer2 protocol, corresponding to Impala port 21050. Impala supports Kerberos authentication with
          all the supported versions of the driver, and requires ODBC 2.05.13 for Impala or higher for LDAP username/password
          authentication.
        </p>

        <p>
          Version 1.x of the Cloudera ODBC Connector uses the original HiveServer1 protocol, corresponding to Impala
          port 21000.
        </p>

      </conbody>
    </concept>

    <concept id="odbc_demo">
      <title>Example of Setting Up an ODBC Application for Impala</title>
      <conbody>

        <p>
          To illustrate the outline of the setup process, here is a transcript of a session to set up
          all required drivers and a business intelligence application
          that uses the ODBC driver, under Mac OS X. Each <codeph>.dmg</codeph> file runs a GUI-based
          installer, first for the <xref href="http://www.iodbc.org/dataspace/iodbc/wiki/iODBC/Downloads" scope="external" format="html">underlying IODBC driver</xref> needed for non-Windows systems, then for
          the Cloudera ODBC Connector, and finally for the BI tool itself.
        </p>

<codeblock>$ ls -1
Cloudera-ODBC-Driver-for-Impala-Install-Guide.pdf
BI_Tool_Installer.dmg
iodbc-sdk-3.52.7-macosx-10.5.dmg
ClouderaImpalaODBC.dmg
$ open iodbc-sdk-3.52.7-macosx-10.dmg
<varname>Install the IODBC driver using its installer</varname>
$ open ClouderaImpalaODBC.dmg
<varname>Install the Cloudera ODBC Connector using its installer</varname>
$ installer_dir=$(pwd)
$ cd /opt/cloudera/impalaodbc
$ ls -1
Cloudera ODBC Driver for Impala Install Guide.pdf
Readme.txt
Setup
lib
ErrorMessages
Release Notes.txt
Tools
$ cd Setup
$ ls
odbc.ini    odbcinst.ini
$ cp odbc.ini ~/.odbc.ini
$ vi ~/.odbc.ini
$ cat ~/.odbc.ini
[ODBC]
# Specify any global ODBC configuration here such as ODBC tracing.

[ODBC Data Sources]
Sample Cloudera Impala DSN=Cloudera ODBC Driver for Impala

[Sample Cloudera Impala DSN]

# Description: DSN Description.
# This key is not necessary and is only to give a description of the data source.
Description=Cloudera ODBC Driver for Impala DSN

# Driver: The location where the ODBC driver is installed to.
Driver=/opt/cloudera/impalaodbc/lib/universal/libclouderaimpalaodbc.dylib

# The DriverUnicodeEncoding setting is only used for SimbaDM
# When set to 1, SimbaDM runs in UTF-16 mode.
# When set to 2, SimbaDM runs in UTF-8 mode.
#DriverUnicodeEncoding=2

# Values for HOST, PORT, KrbFQDN, and KrbServiceName should be set here.
# They can also be specified on the connection string.
HOST=hostname.sample.example.com
PORT=21050
Schema=default

# The authentication mechanism.
# 0 - No authentication (NOSASL)
# 1 - Kerberos authentication (SASL)
# 2 - Username authentication (SASL)
# 3 - Username/password authentication (SASL)
# 4 - Username/password authentication with SSL (SASL)
# 5 - No authentication with SSL (NOSASL)
# 6 - Username/password authentication (NOSASL)
AuthMech=0

# Kerberos related settings.
KrbFQDN=
KrbRealm=
KrbServiceName=

# Username/password authentication with SSL settings.
UID=
PWD
CAIssuedCertNamesMismatch=1
TrustedCerts=/opt/cloudera/impalaodbc/lib/universal/cacerts.pem

# Specify the proxy user ID to use.
#DelegationUID=

# General settings
TSaslTransportBufSize=1000
RowsFetchedPerBlock=10000
SocketTimeout=0
StringColumnLength=32767
UseNativeQuery=0
$ pwd
/opt/cloudera/impalaodbc/Setup
$ cd $installer_dir
$ open BI_Tool_Installer.dmg
<varname>Install the BI tool using its installer</varname>
$ ls /Applications | grep BI_Tool
BI_Tool.app
$ open -a BI_Tool.app
<varname>In the BI tool, connect to a data source using port 21050</varname>
</codeblock>

    </conbody>
  </concept>

  <concept rev="2.3.0" id="jdbc_odbc_notes">
    <title>Notes about JDBC and ODBC Interaction with Impala SQL Features</title>
    <conbody>

      <p>
        Most Impala SQL features work equivalently through the <cmdname>impala-shell</cmdname> interpreter
        of the JDBC or ODBC APIs. The following are some exceptions to keep in mind when switching between
        the interactive shell and applications using the APIs:
      </p>

      <note conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/proxy_jdbc_caveat"/>

      <ul>
        <li>
          <p conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/jdbc_odbc_complex_types"/>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/jdbc_odbc_complex_types_views"/>
        </li>
      </ul>

    </conbody>
  </concept>

</concept>
