<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept rev="1.1" id="authorization">

  <title>Impala Authorization</title>

  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <data name="Category" value="Security"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Sentry"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Impala"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Configuring"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Starting and Stopping"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Users"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Groups"/>
      <data name="Category" value="Administrators"/>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>

  <conbody id="sentry">

    <p>
      Authorization determines which users are allowed to access which resources, and what
      operations they are allowed to perform. You use Apache Ranger for authorization.
      By default, when authorization is not enabled, Impala does all read and
      write operations with the privileges of the <codeph>impala</codeph> user, which is
      suitable for a development/test environment but not for a secure production environment.
      When authorization is enabled, Impala uses the OS user ID of the user who runs
      <cmdname>impala-shell</cmdname> or other client programs, and associates various
      privileges with each user.
    </p>

    <p audience="PDF" outputclass="toc inpage">
      See the following sections for details about using the Impala authorization features.
    </p>

  </conbody>

  <concept id="sentry_priv_model">

    <title>The Privilege Model</title>

    <conbody>

      <p>
        Privileges can be granted on different objects in the schema. Any privilege that can be
        granted is associated with a level in the object hierarchy. If a privilege is granted on
        a parent object in the hierarchy, the child object automatically inherits it. This is
        the same privilege model as Hive and other database systems.
      </p>

      <p>
        The objects in the Impala schema hierarchy are:
      </p>

<codeblock>Server
    URI
    Database
        Table
            Column
</codeblock>

      <p rev="2.3.0 collevelauth">
        The table-level privileges apply to views as well. Anywhere you specify a table name,
        you can specify a view name instead.
      </p>

      <p rev="2.3.0 collevelauth">
        In <keyword keyref="impala23_full"/> and higher, you can specify privileges for
        individual columns.
      </p>

      <p conref="../shared/impala_common.xml#common/privileges_objects"/>

      <p>
        Privileges are managed via the <codeph>GRANT</codeph> and <codeph>REVOKE</codeph> SQL
        statements that require the Ranger service enabled.
      </p>

      <p>
        If you change privileges outside of Impala, e.g. adding a user, removing a user,
        modifying privileges, you must clear the Impala Catalog server cache by running the
        <codeph>REFRESH AUTHORIZATION</codeph> statement. <codeph>REFRESH AUTHORIZATION</codeph>
        is not required if you make the changes to privileges within Impala.
      </p>

    </conbody>

  </concept>

  <concept id="concept_fgf_smj_bjb">

    <title>Object Ownership in Ranger</title>

    <conbody>

      <p>
        Object ownership for tables, views and databases is enabled by default in Impala.
      </p>

      <p>
        To define owner specific privileges, go to ranger UI and define appropriate policies on
        the <codeph>{OWNER}</codeph> user.
      </p>

      <p>
        The <codeph>CREATE</codeph> statements implicitly make the user running the statement
        the owner of the object. For example, if <varname>User A</varname> creates a database,
        <varname>foo</varname>, via the <codeph>CREATE DATABASE</codeph> statement,
        <varname>User A</varname> now owns the <varname>foo</varname> database and is authorized
        to perform any operation on the <varname>foo</varname> database.
      </p>

      <p>
        An ownership can be transferred to another user or role via the <codeph>ALTER
        DATABASE</codeph>, <codeph>ALTER TABLE</codeph>, or <codeph>ALTER VIEW</codeph> with the
        <codeph>SET OWNER</codeph> clause.
      </p>

      <note id="impala-8937">
        Currently, due to a known issue
        (<xref
          href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/IMPALA-8937" format="html"
          scope="external">IMPALA-8937</xref>),
        until the ownership information is fully loaded in the coordinator catalog cache, the
        owner of a table might not be able to see the table when executing the <codeph>SHOW
        TABLES</codeph> statement The owner can still query the table.
      </note>

    </conbody>

  </concept>

  <concept id="enable_ranger_authz">

    <title>Starting Impala with Ranger Authorization Enabled</title>

    <conbody>

      <p>
        To enable authorization in an Impala cluster using Ranger:
      </p>

      <ol>
        <li>
          Add the following options to the <codeph>IMPALA_SERVER_ARGS</codeph> and the
          <codeph>IMPALA_CATALOG_ARGS</codeph> settings in the
          <filepath>/etc/default/impala</filepath> configuration file:
          <ul>
            <li>
              <codeph>-server_name</codeph>: Specify the same name for all
              <cmdname>impalad</cmdname> nodes and the <codeph>catalogd</codeph> in the cluster. </li>
            <li>
              <codeph>-ranger_service_type=hive</codeph>
            </li>
            <li>
              <codeph>-ranger_app_id</codeph>: Set it to the Ranger application id. </li>
            <li>
              <codeph>-authorization_provider=ranger</codeph>
            </li>
          </ul>
        </li>

        <li>
          Restart the <codeph>catalogd</codeph> and all <cmdname>impalad</cmdname> daemons.
        </li>
      </ol>

    </conbody>

  </concept>

  <concept id="sentry_service">

    <title>Managing Privileges</title>

    <conbody>

      <p>
        You set up privileges through the <codeph>GRANT</codeph> and <codeph>REVOKE</codeph>
        statements in either Impala or Hive.
      </p>

      <p>
        For information about using the Impala <codeph>GRANT</codeph> and
        <codeph>REVOKE</codeph> statements, see <xref
          href="impala_grant.xml#grant"/>
        and <xref
          href="impala_revoke.xml#revoke"/>.
      </p>

    </conbody>

    <concept id="changing_privileges">

      <title>Changing Privileges from Outside of Impala</title>

      <conbody>

        <p>
          If you make a change to privileges in Ranger from outside of Impala, e.g.
          adding a user, removing a user, modifying privileges, there are two options to
          propagate the change:
        </p>

        <ul>
          <li>
            Use the <codeph>ranger.plugin.hive.policy.pollIntervalMs</codeph> property to
            specify how often to do a Ranger refresh. The property is specified in
            <codeph>ranger-hive-security.xml</codeph> in the <codeph>conf</codeph> directory
            under your Impala home directory.
          </li>

          <li>
            Run the <codeph>INVALIDATE METADATA</codeph> or <codeph>REFRESH
            AUTHORIZATION</codeph> statement to force a refresh.
          </li>
        </ul>

        <p>
          If you make a change to privileges within Impala, <codeph>INVALIDATE METADATA</codeph>
          is not required.
        </p>

        <note type="warning">
          As <codeph>INVALIDATE METADATA</codeph> is an expensive operation, you should use it
          judiciously.
        </note>

      </conbody>

    </concept>

    <concept id="granting_on_uri">

      <title>Granting Privileges on URI</title>

      <conbody>

        <p> URIs represent the file paths you specify as part of statements such as <codeph>CREATE
            EXTERNAL TABLE</codeph> and <codeph>LOAD DATA</codeph>. Typically, you specify what look
          like UNIX paths, but these locations can also be prefixed with <codeph>hdfs://</codeph> to
          make clear that they are really URIs. To set privileges for a URI, specify the name of a
          directory, and the privilege applies to all the files in that directory. </p>

        <p>
          URIs must start with <codeph>hdfs://</codeph>, <codeph>s3a://</codeph>,
          <codeph>adl://</codeph>, or <codeph>file://</codeph>. If a URI starts with an absolute
          path, the path will be appended to the default filesystem prefix. For example, if you
          specify:
<codeblock>
GRANT ALL ON URI '/tmp';
</codeblock>
          The above statement effectively becomes the following where the default filesystem is
          HDFS.
<codeblock>
GRANT ALL ON URI 'hdfs://localhost:20500/tmp';
</codeblock>
        </p>

        <p>
          When defining URIs for HDFS, you must also specify the NameNode. For example:
<codeblock>GRANT ALL ON URI file:///path/to/dir TO &lt;role>
GRANT ALL ON URI hdfs://namenode:port/path/to/dir TO &lt;role></codeblock>
          <note type="warning">
            Because the NameNode host and port must be specified, it is strongly recommended
            that you use High Availability (HA). This ensures that the URI will remain constant
            even if the NameNode changes. For example:
<codeblock>GRANT ALL ON URI hdfs://ha-nn-uri/path/to/dir TO &lt;role></codeblock>
          </note>
        </p>

      </conbody>

    </concept>

    <concept id="concept_k45_lbm_f2b">

      <title>Examples of Setting up Authorization for Security Scenarios</title>

      <conbody>

        <p>
          The following examples show how to set up authorization to grant privileges on objects
          to groups of users via roles.
        </p>

        <example>
          <title>A User with No Privileges</title>
          <p>
            If a user has no privileges at all, that user cannot access any schema objects in the
            system. The error messages do not disclose the names or existence of objects that the
            user is not authorized to read.
          </p>
          <p>
            This is the experience you want a user to have if they somehow log into a system where
            they are not an authorized Impala user. Or in a real deployment, a user might have no
            privileges because they are not a member of any of the authorized groups.
          </p>
        </example>

        <example>
          <title>Examples of Privileges for Administrative Users</title>
          <p>
            In this example, the SQL statements grant the <codeph>entire_server</codeph> role all
            privileges on both the databases and URIs within the server.
          </p>

<codeblock>CREATE ROLE entire_server;
GRANT ROLE entire_server TO GROUP admin_group;
GRANT ALL ON SERVER server1 TO ROLE entire_server;
</codeblock>
        </example>

        <example>
          <title>A User with Privileges for Specific Databases and Tables</title>
          <p>
            If a user has privileges for specific tables in specific databases, the user can
            access those things but nothing else. They can see the tables and their parent databases
            in the output of <codeph>SHOW TABLES</codeph> and <codeph>SHOW DATABASES</codeph>,
            <codeph>USE</codeph> the appropriate databases, and perform the relevant actions
            (<codeph>SELECT</codeph> and/or <codeph>INSERT</codeph>) based on the table
            privileges. To actually create a table requires the <codeph>ALL</codeph> privilege at
            the database level, so you might define separate roles for the user that sets up a
            schema and other users or applications that perform day-to-day operations on the tables.
          </p>
<codeblock>
CREATE ROLE one_database;
GRANT ROLE one_database TO GROUP admin_group;
GRANT ALL ON DATABASE db1 TO ROLE one_database;

CREATE ROLE instructor;
GRANT ROLE instructor TO GROUP trainers;
GRANT ALL ON TABLE db1.lesson TO ROLE instructor;

# This particular course is all about queries, so the students can SELECT but not INSERT or CREATE/DROP.
CREATE ROLE student;
GRANT ROLE student TO GROUP visitors;
GRANT SELECT ON TABLE db1.training TO ROLE student;</codeblock>
        </example>

        <example>
          <title>Privileges for Working with External Data Files</title>
          <p> When data is being inserted through the <codeph>LOAD DATA</codeph> statement or is
            referenced from an HDFS location outside the normal Impala database directories, the
            user also needs appropriate permissions on the URIs corresponding to those HDFS
            locations. </p>
          <p> In this example: </p>
          <ul>
            <li> The <codeph>external_table</codeph> role can insert into and query the Impala
              table, <codeph>external_table.sample</codeph>. </li>

            <li> The <codeph>staging_dir</codeph> role can specify the HDFS path
                <filepath>/user/impala-user/external_data</filepath> with the <codeph>LOAD
                DATA</codeph> statement. When Impala queries or loads data files, it operates on all
              the files in that directory, not just a single file, so any Impala
                <codeph>LOCATION</codeph> parameters refer to a directory rather than an individual
              file. </li>
          </ul>
          <codeblock>CREATE ROLE external_table;
GRANT ROLE external_table TO GROUP impala_users;
GRANT ALL ON TABLE external_table.sample TO ROLE external_table;

CREATE ROLE staging_dir;
GRANT ROLE staging TO GROUP impala_users;
GRANT ALL ON URI 'hdfs://127.0.0.1:8020/user/impala-user/external_data' TO ROLE staging_dir;</codeblock>
        </example>

        <example>
          <title>Separating Administrator Responsibility from Read and Write Privileges</title>
          <p> To create a database, you need the full privilege on that database while day-to-day
            operations on tables within that database can be performed with lower levels of
            privilege on a specific table. Thus, you might set up separate roles for each database
            or application: an administrative one that could create or drop the database, and a
            user-level one that can access only the relevant tables. </p>
          <p> In this example, the responsibilities are divided between users in 3 different groups: </p>
          <ul>
            <li> Members of the <codeph>supergroup</codeph> group have the
                <codeph>training_sysadmin</codeph> role and so can set up a database named
                <codeph>training</codeph>. </li>

            <li> Members of the <codeph>impala_users</codeph> group have the
                <codeph>instructor</codeph> role and so can create, insert into, and query any
              tables in the <codeph>training</codeph> database, but cannot create or drop the
              database itself. </li>

            <li> Members of the <codeph>visitor</codeph> group have the <codeph>student</codeph>
              role and so can query those tables in the <codeph>training</codeph> database. </li>
          </ul>
          <codeblock>CREATE ROLE training_sysadmin;
GRANT ROLE training_sysadmin TO GROUP supergroup;
GRANT ALL ON DATABASE training TO ROLE training_sysadmin;

CREATE ROLE instructor;
GRANT ROLE instructor TO GROUP impala_users;
GRANT ALL ON TABLE training.course1 TO ROLE instructor;

CREATE ROLE student;
GRANT ROLE student TO GROUP visitor;
GRANT SELECT ON TABLE training.course1 TO ROLE student;</codeblock>
        </example>

      </conbody>

    </concept>

  </concept>

  <concept id="security_schema">

    <title>Setting Up Schema Objects for a Secure Impala Deployment</title>

    <conbody>

      <p>
        In your role definitions, you must specify privileges at the level of individual
        databases and tables, or all databases or all tables within a database. To simplify the
        structure of these rules, plan ahead of time how to name your schema objects so that
        data with different authorization requirements are divided into separate databases.
      </p>

      <p>
        If you are adding security on top of an existing Impala deployment, you can rename
        tables or even move them between databases using the <codeph>ALTER TABLE</codeph>
        statement.
      </p>

    </conbody>

  </concept>

  <concept id="sec_ex_default">

    <title>The DEFAULT Database in a Secure Deployment</title>

    <conbody>

      <p>
        Because of the extra emphasis on granular access controls in a secure deployment, you
        should move any important or sensitive information out of the <codeph>DEFAULT</codeph>
        database into a named database. Sometimes you might need to give privileges on the
        <codeph>DEFAULT</codeph> database for administrative reasons, for example, as a place
        you can reliably specify with a <codeph>USE</codeph> statement when preparing to drop a
        database.
      </p>

    </conbody>

  </concept>
  <concept id="sec_ranger_col_masking">
    <title>Ranger Column Masking</title>
    <conbody>
    <p> Ranger column masking hides sensitive columnar data in Impala query output. For example, you
        can define a policy that reveals only the first or last four characters of column data.
        Column masking is enabled by default. The Impala behavior mimics Hive behavior with respect
        to column masking. For more information, see the <xref
          href="https://cwiki.apache.org/confluence/display/RANGER/Row-level+filtering+and+column-masking+using+Apache+Ranger+policies+in+Apache+Hive"
          format="html" scope="external">Apache Ranger documentation</xref>.</p>

      <p>
        The following table lists all supported, built-in mask types for defining column masking in
        a policy using the Ranger REST API. <table rowsep="1" colsep="1" id="table_mask_types">
          <tgroup cols="4">
            <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
            <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
            <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3"/>
            <colspec colname="c4" colnum="4"/>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Type</entry>
                <entry>Name</entry>
                <entry>Description</entry>
                <entry>Transformer</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>MASK</entry>
                <entry>Redact</entry>
                <entry>Replace lowercase with 'x', uppercase with 'X', digits with '0'</entry>
                <entry>mask({col})</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>MASK_SHOW_LAST_4</entry>
                <entry>Partial mask: show last 4</entry>
                <entry>Show last 4 characters; replace rest with 'x'</entry>
                <entry>mask_show_last_n({col}, 4, 'x', 'x', 'x', -1, '1')</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>MASK_SHOW_FIRST_4</entry>
                <entry>Partial mask: show first 4</entry>
                <entry>Show first 4 characters; replace rest with 'x'</entry>
                <entry>mask_show_first_n({col}, 4, 'x', 'x', 'x', -1, '1')</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>MASK_HASH</entry>
                <entry>Hash</entry>
                <entry>Hash the value</entry>
                <entry>mask_hash({col})</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>MASK_NULL</entry>
                <entry>Nullify</entry>
                <entry>Replace with NULL</entry>
                <entry> N/A</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>MASK_NONE</entry>
                <entry>Unmasked (retain original value)</entry>
                <entry>No masking</entry>
                <entry> N/A</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>MASK_DATE_SHOW_YEAR</entry>
                <entry>Date: show only year</entry>
                <entry>Date: show only year</entry>
                <entry>mask({col}, 'x', 'x', 'x', -1, '1', 1, 0, -1)</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>CUSTOM</entry>
                <entry>Custom</entry>
                <entry>Custom</entry>
                <entry>N/A</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </p>
    </conbody>
  </concept>
<concept id="lim_on_mask_functions">
  <title>Limitations on Mask Functions</title>
    <conbody>
      <p>The mask functions in Hive are implemented through GenericUDFs. Even though Impala users
        can call Hive UDFs, Impala does not yet support Hive GenericUDFs, so you cannot use Hive's
        mask functions in Impala. However, Impala has builtin mask functions that are implemented
        through overloads. In Impala, when using mask functions, not all parameter combinations are
        supported. These mask functions are introduced in Impala 3.4</p>
      <p>The following list includes all the implemented overloads.</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Overloads used by Ranger default masking policies,</li>
        <li>Overloads with simple arguments,</li>
        <li>Overload with all arguments in <codeph>int</codeph> type for full functionality. Char
          argument needs to be converted to their ASCII value.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>To list the available overloads, use the following query:</p>
      <codeblock>show functions in _impala_builtins like "mask*";</codeblock>
      <note>
        <ul>
          <li>An error message that states "<i>No matching function with signature: mask...</i>"
            implies that Impala does not contain the corresponding overload.</li>
        </ul>
      </note>
    </conbody>
</concept>
</concept>
